Guide to the Immanuel Wallerstein Collection of African Liberation Movement Posters
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Immanuel Wallerstein collection of African liberation movement posters
1960-2008
MS 1865
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2
The collection consists of posters acquired by Immanuel Wallerstein which document liberation movements in numerous African countries. Accession 2015-M-001 contains material from a 2008 exhibit on the posters.
Wallerstein, Immanuel Maurice, 1930-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Immanuel Wallerstein, 2005; transferred from African Collection Curator, 2014.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Immanuel Wallerstein was born on September 28, 1930, in New York City. He received a B.A. (1951), M.A. (1954), and Ph.D. (1959) from Columbia University. Wallerstein occupied positions in the sociology departments of Columbia University (1958-1971), McGill University (1971-1976), Ecole des Hautes Etudes en Sciences Sociales (1975-1976, 1980-1981, 1983-1995), and Binghamton University (SUNY) (1976-1999, emeritus). In 2000 he joined Yale University as senior research scholar. He served as president of the African Studies Association (1973-1974), president of the International Sociological Association (1994-1998), and chair of the international Gulbenkian Commission on the Restructuring of the Social Sciences (1993-1995). He is a Fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences. Wallerstein has written extensively on African topics and issues.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of posters acquired by Immanuel Wallerstein which document liberation movements in numerous African countries. Accession 2015-M-001 contains material from a 2008 exhibit on the posters.
National liberation movements -- Africa; Posters -- Africa; Wallerstein, Immanuel Maurice, 1930-
- Inventory
  Scope and Contents
  The African liberation movement posters are arranged by their format: calendars, photograph exhibits, and individual posters. Within these categories, they are arranged alphabetically by the name of the organization/person responsible for the poster, or by poster title.
  - Calendars
    - African National Congress, [1972]-1975, 1978-1980, 1983, [1993] (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - American Committee on Africa, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - International Defence and Aid Fund for Southern Africa, 1974, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Kenya National Fund, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Liberation Support Movement, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - SWAPO (South West Africa People's Organization), 1977, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photograph exhibits
    - International Defence and Aid Fund for Southern Africa, "Zimbabwe in Struggle", [1977] (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Komitee Zuidelijk Afrika [photographs of Angola, Namibia, and South Africa], [1976], undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Posters
    - African National Congress, 1982, 1987, undated (Box 2)
    - Anti-Apartheid Movement, undated (Box 2)
    - Associação de Amizade Portugal -R.P. Angola, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Associação Portugal/Angola, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Black Artist for a Free Africa, undated (Box 2)
    - Comité de Solidarité de la République Démocratique Allemande and Nations Unies contre l'Apartheid, undated (Box 2)
    - Committee for a Free Mozambique, [1970] (Box 2)
    - Développement et Paix, Oxfam, Rallyes Tiers-Monde, and SUCO, undated (Box 2)
    - Dhlomo, Bongine, "Woman: More Than Just A Man's Spare Rib", undated (Box 2)
    - E.P.L.F. (Eritrean Peoples Liberation Forces), 1976, undated (Box 2)
    - Freedom Concert, undated (Box 2)
    - FRELIMO (Mozambique Liberation Front), undated (Box 2)
    - Holland Committee on Southern Africa, undated (Box 2)
    - "I Am Prepared to Die," [with picture of Nelson Mandela], undated (Box 3)
    - Liberation Support Movement/United Nations Centre Against Apartheid, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Movement for the Liberation of Angola, [1971], 1972, undated (Box 3)
    - Partido Africano da Independência da Guinée Cabo Verde (PAIGC)/Amilcar Cabral, undated (Box 3)
    - Portuguese-British Alliance, undated (Box 3)
    - Solidarity with African Women in Struggle, undated (Box 3)
    - Southern Africa Information Group, undated (Box 3)
    - SWAPO (South West Africa People's Organization), 1978, 1980, 1984 (Box 3)
    - United Nations Department of Public Information/United Nations Council for Namibia, 1984, undated (Box 3)
    - Unterdrückung in Südafrika -Wie lange noch?, C----, Robert, undated (Box 3)
- Additional material, 2007-2008; Accession 2015-M-001; 1
  - Poster exhibit material, 2007-2008 (Box 1, Folder 1)